I'm now going to be doing דף ע"ו Daf Ayin-Vav 76, doing
it offline so we can catch up, and we're going to pick
up and continue on the top of ע"ו Ayin-Vav
from אימהו. Imahu. It is one, two, three, four, five lines from
the top, and this is the גמרא Gemara continuing to work out
the issues about daughter and granddaughter and mother and mother-in-law and grandmother-in-law
and so on. Okay, so we have the whole series of comparisons
basically about his daughters and her daughters and her mother, and all
of those are forbidden and get שרפה. Sreifa. So now the גמרא
Gemara says, "One minute, אימהו, Imahu, her mother-in-law is forbidden, if her
daughter-in-law is forbidden." And we know that his daughter-in-law, his son's wife,
is forbidden to him, even after his son, even when she's no
longer an אשת איש, Eshet Ish, even after his son let's say
were to divorce her or something, but her daughter-in-law is not forbidden
to him. So if her son, her step-son marries a woman, that's
not included, but why don't we say that since we've made everything
else parallel in terms of the punishment of שרפה, Sreifa, that by
analogy her daughter-in-law should also be forbidden to him? I mean her
daughter-in-law, his step-daughter-in-law should be forbidden to him. So אמר אביי, Amar
Abaye, אביי Abaye says, אמר קרא אשת בנך היא, Amar Kra Eshet
Bincha Hi, no, the prohibition of daughter-in-law says she is your son's
wife. משום אשת בנך אתה מחייבו ואי אתה מחייבו משום אשת בנו,
Mishum Eshet Bincha Atta Mechayvo V'ee Atta Mechayvo Mishum Eshet Bino, that
the only issue is when it's your son's wife, not your step-son's
wife. רבא אמר, Rava Amar, רבא Rava has a different answer. So
אביי, Abaye, similar to what we said before about the issue about
his grandmother, אביי Abaye goes to a פסוק. Pasuk. רבא Rava does
it by logic and says that the basic analogy will fail. בין
למאן דאמר דון מינה ומינה בין למאן דאמר דון מינה ואוקימה באתרה,
Bein L'man D'amar Don Minah U'minah Bein L'man D'amar Don Minah V'okimah
B'atrah, whether when you learn something you take it with its context,
דון מינה ומינה, Don Minah U'minah, or whether you look at you
take it and then apply it in its local context, דון מינה
ואוקימה באתרה, Don Minah V'okimah B'atrah, לא אתיא, Lo Asya, it won't
work, you can't make the analogy. Let's figure this out. למאן דאמר
דון מינה ומינה, L'man D'amar Don Minah U'minah, if you learn it
with its original context, מה הוא כלתו אסורה אף היא כלתו אסורה,
Ma Hu Kalato Asura Af Hi Kalato Asura, the same way for,
you know, his daughter-in-law, his daughter-in-law should be forbidden to him, so
her daughter-in-law, his step-daughter-in-law should be forbidden to him. One minute, ומינה,
U'minah, and then with its context. So the context here always means
not just that it's forbidden, but what is the מיתה? Mita? So
with its context, מה הוא בסקילה אף היא בסקילה, Ma Hu Bi'skila
Af Hi Bi'skila, so the same way his daughter-in-law, her prohibition is
punishable by stoning, her step-daughter-in-law by the analogy she should be by
stoning because I'm taking it with its context. So although it's her
daughter-in-law, it gets the original context of stoning. So that won't work.
Why won't that work? Because למאן דאמר סקילה חמורה, L'man D'amar Skila
Chamura, if סקילה Skila is weightier than שרפה, Sreifa, איכא למיפרך, Ika
Lemifrach, מה להלן שכן אמו בסקילה תאמר בהי שכן אמו בשרפה. Ma
Lehalan Shekein Imo Bi'skila Tomar Behi Shekein Imo Bi'sreifa. You can't apply
his prohibitions to her prohibitions because his prohibitions, he's בסקילה Bi'skila and
those are weightier, and the prohibitions on her side are all שרפה
Sreifa prohibitions. So therefore, you can't assume that what you take from
his side and apply it to her side. So just because his
daughter-in-law is forbidden, doesn't mean that her daughter-in-law will be
forbidden. ועוד, V'od, and in
addition, בת בשרפה וכלתה בסקילה, Bita Bi'sreifa V'chalata Bi'skila, anyway there would
be an inconsistency because we would say that his daughter would be
בשרפה, Bi'sreifa,
that her daughter we know for him is שרפה, Sreifa, and her
daughter-in-law according to this would be סקילה. Skila. And that doesn't make
sense, that's being inconsistent, it's actually not only inconsistent, it's more weightier
by the daughter-in-law, and we're assuming here that because we're assuming סקילה
Skila is weightier. So the גמרא Gemara says, "You know what? That
wouldn't be a problem."
The גמרא Gemara says, one minute,
הוא עצמו יוכיח דבתו בשרפה וכלתו בסקילה. Hu Atzmo Yochiach Dibito Bi'sreifa
V'chalato Bi'skila. Well, what do you mean? I mean the same would
be true about him. We've his daughter is שרפה Sreifa and his
daughter-in-law is סקילה, Skila, and if סקילה Skila is more חמורה, Chamora,
that's just the way it is, even though it doesn't make sense,
so you can't ask that on this comparison. Okay, but here's what
you would ask, אלא מהו לא חילקת בו בין אמו לכלתו, Ela
Mahu Lo Chilakta Bo Bein Imo L'chalato, for him his mother is
סקילה Skila and his daughter-in-law is סקילה. Skila. So all the things
that are not based on daughters are by סקילה Skila when it's
on his side. But here, if we applied daughter-in-law to her and
keep it with the context of סקילה, Skila, there's going to be
an inconsistency between mother and daughter-in-law. אף היא לא תחלוק בה בין
אמו לכלתו. Af Hi Lo Tachlok Bah Bein Imo L'chalato. Okay, and
therefore that inconsistency means that you can't do the analogy. ולמאן דאמר
שרפה חמורה מהאי קושיא נמי לא נדוני. Ul'man D'amar Sreifa Chamura Mehai
Kushya Nami Lo Nadoni. So therefore and even if שרפה Sreifa was
weightier, and so one of the earlier counters would fall off, this
challenge remains, that it wouldn't be analogous. That him, the mother and
the daughter-in-law are the same, and for her, the mother is שרפה
Sreifa and the daughter-in-law would be סקילה. Skila. So that makes that
not possible. That's if you say דון מינה ומינה, Don Minah U'minah,
keep the original context. ולמאן דאמר דון מינה ואוקימה באתרה, Ul'man D'amar
Don Minah V'okimah B'atrah,
and if you take it and apply the local context, מה הוא
כלתו אסורה אף היא כלתו אסורה, Ma Hu Kalato Asura Af Hi
Kalato Asura, the same way for, you know, the thing you're learning
out. his daughter-in-law is forbidden, so her daughter-in-law, his stepdaughter, is forbidden.
So and now וְאוֹקֵי בְּאַתְרֵיהּ, V'Okei B'atrah, that's the מִינָּהּ Minah וְאוֹקֵי
בְּאַתְרֵיהּ V'Okei B'atrah now apply the context. What's the context? הָתָם הוּא
דְּבִסְקִילָה אֲבָל הָכָא בִּשְׂרֵפָה Hasam hu d'biskila aval hacha b'sreifa
that there it came from a case by him, it was skila,
but you apply the context of the wife's side of the family
as it were and you say sreifa. Okay, so now we're not
going to have an inconsistency because her mother's going to be בִּשְׂרֵפָה,
b'sreifa, her daughter's going to be בִּשְׂרֵפָה, b'sreifa, her daughter-in-law's going to
be בִּשְׂרֵפָה. b'sreifa. But one minute. הָתָם הוּא דְּבִסְקִילָה אֲבָל הָכָא בִּשְׂרֵפָה
Hasam hu d'biskila aval hacha b'sreifa
like we find by אִמָּהּ, imah, right? All the cases of the
wife's side of the family—mother, daughter, and now daughter-in-law—will be שְׂרֵפָה. sreifa.
That's putting it in the context. So here's why that won't work.
לְמַאן דְּאָמַר סְקִילָה חֲמוּרָה, L'man d'amar skila chamurah, if you assume skila
is weightier, that's that throws off the entire analogy because just because
things that his side is weightier because it gets skila by some
of them, so you can't apply it to her side. אִיכָּא לְמִפְרַךְ
מָה לְהוּ שֶׁכֵּן אִמּוֹ בִּסְקִילָה. Ika l'mifrach mah l'hu sheken imo biskila.
So in his side of the family, the mother is skila. תֹּאמַר
בְּזוֹ שֶׁאִמָּהּ בִּשְׂרֵפָה, Tomar b'zo she'imah b'sreifa, but when it's her mother,
it's sreifa. So therefore clearly his side is weightier. So just because
for him daughter-in-law is forbidden, it doesn't mean daughter-in-law will be forbidden
when it's her daughter-in-law. וְעוֹד, V'od, and here's another point, which is
מָה הוּא חָלַקְתָּ בּוֹ בֵּין בִּתּוֹ לְכַלָּתוֹ. mah hu chalakta bo bein
bito l'chalaso. For him, there's a difference. His daughter is שְׂרֵפָה, sreifa,
his daughter-in-law—so now we're actually trying to say the analogy has to
maintain a difference, the different set that was in the original case.
His daughter is שְׂרֵפָה, sreifa, his daughter-in-law is סְקִילָה. skila. אַף הִיא,
Af hi, so now because we put this in its context and
we gave it שְׂרֵפָה sreifa because the mother was שְׂרֵפָה, sreifa, you're
now losing the dissimilarity. תַּחְלֹוק, Tachlok, you have to make a distinction
בֵּין בִּתָּהּ לְכַלָּתָהּ. bein bitah l'chalasa. So therefore, וּלְמַאן דְּאָמַר נַמִי שְׂרֵפָה
חֲמוּרָה, u'l'man d'amar nami sreifa chamurah, so even if sreifa is weightier
and you don't have the first question, מֵהַאי קוּשְׁיָא לָא נִידּוֹן. me'hai
kushya lo nidon. This second thing prevents it because it's not going
to be analogous. The analogy would require a different type of a
מִיתָה misah between the daughter and the daughter-in-law, but that you can't
do because the context demands that it's the same מִיתָה. misah. Okay,
so that's basically whether Abaye and Rava, they have different ways of
learning it, but they learned that on his side you cannot forbid
the grandmother and on her side you cannot forbid the
daughter-in-law. So now the Gemara says like this: Now we have a
different question. The one thing that we did not solve from the
previous דַּף daf was how do you know his daughter when it's
not his wife's daughter is going to be forbidden. The Torah only
speaks or punishable. The Torah only speaks about his granddaughter. Okay, so
let's take a look. It says like
this: בִּתּוֹ מֵאֲנוּסָתוֹ, Bito me'anusaso, his daughter from a woman he raped.
Now what's very strange or troubling is that the Gemara describes the
issue of his daughter that is not his wife's daughter as the
daughter from the woman he raped. Rashi of course points out it
could have also been a woman he seduced, right? Or just a
woman that they consensually, right? It doesn't even require seduction. They both
agreed to have this sexual relationship and have a baby out of
wedlock. But for whatever reason, the Gemara distills that scenario as בִּתּוֹ
מֵאֲנוּסָתוֹ, bito me'anusaso, his daughter from the woman he raped. I can't
explain why. It's a disturbing case. Anyway, it says, how do we
know—the Torah refers to his granddaughter when it's not her granddaughter—but it
doesn't refer to his daughter. So the Gemara says like this: בִּתּוֹ
מֵאֲנוּסָתוֹ מִנַּיִן? Bito me'anusaso minayin? אָמַר אַבַּיֵי, Amar Abaye, so Abaye says,
קַל וָחֹמֶר. kal vachomer. It's a קַל וָחֹמֶר. kal vachomer. אֲבַת בִּתּוֹ
עוֹנֶשׁ אֲבִתּוֹ לֹא כָּל שֶׁכֵּן? A bat bito onesh a bito lo
kol sheken? If it's going to punish his granddaughter, it'll certainly punish
his daughter. That's completely reasonable. But now the Gemara says, וְכִי עוֹנְשִׁין
מִן הַדִּין? V'chi onshin min hadin? But since when can you get
punished based on a קַל וָחֹמֶר? kal vachomer? General principle is that
no matter how obvious it is on a קַל וָחֹמֶר, kal vachomer,
for punishment it needs to be explicit. So Gemara says גִּלּוּי מִילְּתָא
בְּעָלְמָא הוּא. gilluy milta b'alma hu. It's not a קַל וָחֹמֶר, kal
vachomer, it's just implicit. Now what makes this implicit and not a
קַל וָחֹמֶר? kal vachomer? So Rashi says because granddaughter is forbidden because
ultimately because she comes through your daughter. So because it ultimately rests
on the assumption that the daughter is forbidden. It's not just a
קַל וָחֹמֶר, kal vachomer, oh granddaughter's going to be forbidden, certainly daughter.
It's that the whole relationship to granddaughter is through the daughter. So
therefore it presumes that daughter's forbidden and then this is an extension
of that. So that's what Abaye says. Daughter forbidden is presumed. Okay.
So Rava
now Rava says, אֲמַר לֵיהּ רַב יִצְחָק בַּר אַבְדִּימִי, amar lei Rav
Yitzchak bar Avdimi, no, we learn it from a גְּזֵירָה שָׁוָה. gezeira
shava. So it's interesting, before Rava was doing סְבָרָא sevara and Abaye
was doing פְּסוּקִים psukim and here it's reversed. אָתְיָא הֵנָּה הֵנָּה אָתְיָא
זִמָּה זִמָּה. Asya hennah hennah asya zimmah zimmah. So if you remember
the way we learned to apply the punishments of daughter—of her daughters
to his daughters—was from the הֵנָּה הֵנָּה. hennah hennah. By both of
them it says... So the same thing that הנה heina link tells
us, her it says explicitly in the פסוק, pasuk, a woman and
her daughter, and then we also said and granddaughter. So even though
on him, when it's his daughter without his wife's daughter, it only
says granddaughter, but the הנה heina link tells us, it's also daughter.
Okay, so even though the פסוקים psukim only told us his granddaughters
and we learned that שריפה, Sreifah, we know his daughter is based
on the link of הנה heina or קל וחומר, Kal Vachomer, גילוי
מילתא. giluy milta. Okay, now that's that now. Now we have a
ברייתא braita though that learns it from a different place. תניא אבוה
דרבי אבין Tanya avuh d'Rabbi Avin Rabbi Avin taught in a ברייתא
braita לפי שלא למדנו לבתו מאנוסתו, lefi shelo lamadnu levito me'anusato, because
the ברייתא braita says how do we know his daughter from a
woman he raped, a daughter not from his wife, how do we
know that's forbidden? So הוצרך הכתוב לומר hutzrach hakatuv lomar so the
ברייתא braita says that the פסוק pasuk had to teach you ובת
איש כהן כי תחל לזנות. uvat ish kohen ki teichel liznot. Now
that case is she's married and she's having sex with another man,
but the דרשה drasha as רש"י Rashi points out is the extra
word איש. ish. It could have said ובת כהן. uvat kohen. So
since it says איש כהן, ish kohen, we're actually learning it that
איש כי תחל ובת איש כי תחל לזנות ish ki teichel uvat
ish ki teichel liznot if the daughter of a man, bracket כהן,
kohen, has forbidden sex with her father, then את אביה היא מחללת
באש תשרף. et aviha hi mchaleles ba'eish tisaref. So that gets you
שריפה Sreifah right there. So not only gets you that it's forbidden,
it explicitly gets you שריפה. Sreifah. Okay. אם בת כהן היא בשריפה
im bat kohen hi b'Sreifah and I'm sorry, I skipped a line.
Oh yes, no, okay. הוצרך הכתוב לומר בת איש כהן. hutzrach hakatuv
lomar bat ish kohen. So now the גמרא Gemara asks a question.
One minute. אם בת כהן היא בשריפה ואין בועלה בשריפה. im bat
kohen hi b'Sreifah v'ein bo'ala b'Sreifah. We have a principle by בת
כהן. bat kohen. It says היא באש תשרף, hi ba'eish tisaref, כי
תחל את אביה היא מחללת באש תשרף. ki teichel et aviha hi
mchaleles ba'eish tisaref. She gets שריפה Sreifah but the man who has
intercourse with her gets the punishment he would have if she weren't
a בת כהן, bat kohen, like חנק. chenek. Okay, so why not
say the same thing here, that if a man has intercourse with
his daughter she gets שריפה Sreifah and he gets something else? No,
that's not true. So the גמרא Gemara says אם בת כהן היא
בשריפה ואין בועלה בשריפה אף בתו מאנוסתו. im bat kohen hi b'Sreifah
v'ein bo'ala b'Sreifah af bito me'anusato. Should we say the same here,
היא בשריפה ואין בועלה בשריפה? hi b'Sreifah v'ein bo'ala b'Sreifah? Maybe we
should say the same if we're going to learn it from the
פסוק. pasuk. אמר אביי אמר קרא את אביה היא מחללת, Amar Abaye
amar kra et aviha hi mchaleles, מי שמחללת את אביה יצא זו
שאביה מחללה. mi shemchaleles et aviha yatza zo she'aviha mchalalah. This principle
היא באש תשרף hi ba'eish tisaref that she gets שריפה Sreifah and
not him is when she is bringing shame and desecration to her
father. But in this case where the father is violating and desecrating
her, so then it will not have that split between which punishment
she gets and the man gets, or here the father gets. רבא
אמר Rava amar רבא Rava says בשלמא התם אפקיתיה מדינא דבת כהן
ואוקמתיה אדינא דבת ישראל. bishlama hatam afkitei midina d'bat kohen v'okamtei adina
d'bat Yisrael. No, there we can split because even if we say
that the man who has intercourse with a בת כהן bat kohen
gets the punishment he would have as if she weren't a בת
כהן, bat kohen, fine, the punishment he would have of a married
woman as if she wasn't a בת כהן bat kohen is still
going to be being put to death, just a different death. So
there you could say don't treat her as a בת כהן bat
kohen and he could still get death to the guy executed. But
הכא אדינא דמאן מוקמת ליה? hacha adina d'man mokmas lei? So here
if we don't treat her like his daughter and he's not going
to get שריפה, Sreifah, so what are we going to treat her
like? אדינא דפנויה, adina d'pnuyah, like a single woman? So מוקמת ליה?
mokmas lei? So then what? So then he's not going to get
punished at all? That's impossible, that she should get punished and he
shouldn't. So since there's no parallel to apply to him, yes he
will get שריפה. Sreifah. So we either learn שריפה Sreifah from a
קל וחומר Kal Vachomer of granddaughter or applying the principle of her
daughters or from this פסוק pasuk of ובת איש כהן. uvat ish
kohen. Now all of that was to tell you that they get
שריפה. Sreifah. Now we're going to talk about how do you know
it's prohibited. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this. אזהרה לבתו
מאנוסתו מנין? azharah levito me'anusato minayin? Where is it explicit that it's
prohibited? בשלמא לאביי ורבא דנפקו להו עונש נפקא נמי להו אזהרה. bishlama
l'Abaye v'Rava d'nafku lehu ones nafka nami lehu azharah. The same place
you learn the punishment, you learn the prohibition. אביי, Abaye, it's implicit
in the biblical prohibition of granddaughter. For רבא, Rava, the link to
her daughters. The same way her daughters are שריפה Sreifah while her
daughters are also of prohibition, so his daughters are prohibition by the
גזירה שוה. gezeirah shavah. אלא דתני אבוה דרבי אבין מאי? ela d'tani
avuh d'Rabbi Avin mai? But according to what we taught father Rabbi
Avin, what can you say? Because that just says את אביה היא
מחללת באש תשרף. et aviha hi mchaleles ba'eish tisaref. So talks about
שריפה Sreifah but it doesn't tell you that it's prohibited. So the
גמרא Gemara says אמר עולא אמר קרא אל תחלל את בתך להזנותה.
amar Ulla amar kra al techalel et bitcha l'haznotah. Do not desecrate
your daughter so that to make her be a whore or something,
to make her fornicate. So we are learning what that means to
make means don't you the man desecrate your daughter in an act
of forbidden sex, in an act of intercourse. So that's the prohibition.
מתיב רבי יעקב אחוה דרבי אחא בר יעקב mativ Rabbi Yaakov achuh
d'Rabbi Acha bar Yaakov Rabbi Yaakov asked on that האי אל תחלל
hai al techalel האי אל תחלל את בתך להזנותה אמרת לה? hai
al techalel et bitcha lehaznotah amrat lah? What are you telling me?
It's coming to prohibit a man having intercourse with his daughter? הא
מיבעי ליה לכדתניא? ha mibei leih lichad'tanya? Like we taught in a
ברייתא, baraita, we need it for that. For what we teach in
a ברייתא: baraita: אל תחלל את בתך להזנותה. al techalel et bitcha
lehaznotah. יכול בכהן המשיא את בתו ללוי ולישראל הכתוב מדבר? yachol b'kohen
hamasi et bito l'Levi u'l'Yisrael hakatuv medaber? Maybe it just means since
this whole thing about daughter anyway is emphasized with the כהן, kohen,
it means a כהן kohen shouldn't marry his daughter off to a
לוי Levi or ישראל. Yisrael. That's a type of being מחללה, mechallelah,
making her חול chol as רש"י Rashi says, connecting her to a
non-holy family, not allowing her to eat תרומה. terumah. תלמוד לומר להזנותה.
talmud lomar lehaznotah. It's not just about making her חול, chol, it's
about doing it through a form of forbidden sex. שבחילול שבזנות הכתוב
מדבר. shebichilul shebiznut hakatuv medaber. It has to be a form of
fornication or forbidden sex. So what would be that case? What is
the פסוק pasuk talking about? במוסר בתו שלא לשם אישות. b'moser bito
shelo l'shem ishut. So this is probably פשט pshat of the פסוקים.
psukim. Do not give over your daughter in a non-marital context. So
that's the case and that's the פשט, pshat, not this case of
a man having intercourse with his daughter. I'm going to get back
to that in a minute, but let's just finish this thought about
it being a basis for forbidden intercourse for a man and his
daughter. So the גמרא Gemara says, where was I? No, אם כן
לימא קרא אל תחל. im ken leima kra al tachal. Don't use
the double ל, lamed, just say do not violate. מאי אל תחלל?
mai al techalel? What's the double ל? lamed? שמע מינה תרתי. shma
mina tarti. Two forms of חולין: chullin: one by giving over his
daughter to a man in a non-marital context, and the other is
a father and his daughter. So that's what we're learning if the
prohibition is based on בתו של כהן—excuse bito shel kohen me—the punishment,
then the prohibition comes from אל תחלל את בתך להזנותה. al techalel
et bitcha lehaznotah. Now within this issue of giving over a daughter
for a non-marital context, it's a really interesting question. Does it mean
like a committed relationship, a one-time act? Or does it mean that
a person is basically pimping his daughter? A man is basically selling
his daughter, having people pay him so his daughter has sex with
random people? So that is a very important question and gets into
a larger issue of the whole question of the הלכה halacha and
the תורה's Torah attitude towards sex outside the context of marriage. Is
any sex outside the context of marriage considered to be זנות? znut?
And there's a major debate of the ראשונים Rishonim whether this idea
אל תחלל את בתך להזנותה al techalel et bitcha lehaznotah is talking
about any type of sex outside of marriage, even a committed relationship
or something, or is it talking about particularly if it's like casual
or any man or it's hiring out the daughter and so on.
Okay, we're going to continue seeing that theme in a minute. Because
now the גמרא Gemara says, we're saying that the תחלל techalel is
a double ל, lamed, a double language, so that it's different for
אביי ורבא. Abaye v'Rava. I'm guessing so it's a double thing. It
could tell you daughter and it could tell you this idea of
מוסר בתו. moser bito. But if you think daughter is forbidden based
on what we learned before implicitly in granddaughter or learned out from
her daughters, so what do you do with the double ל? lamed?
In addition to the prohibition of a man giving over his daughter
לזנות, liznut, what else is prohibited in this פסוק? pasuk? So that's
what the גמרא's Gemara going to ask. ואביי ורבא האי אל תחלל
את בתך להזנותה מאי עבדי ליה? v'Abaye v'Rava hai al techalel et
bitcha lehaznotah mai avdi leih? What do they do with it if
it's a double prohibition? So אמר רב מני, amar Rav Mani, זה
המשיא בתו לזקן. zeh hamasi bito l'zaken. So this is somebody who
marries his daughter off to an elderly man. It does not just
mean that it's not in the context of procreation, that's not the
point. The point is, is that it's a man who cannot satisfy
her sexual needs. Maybe he can't have sex at all, or certainly
can't satisfy her, and it's just asking for trouble. And therefore that
is a type of a marriage that it is essentially going to
be זנות. znut. It's going to cause her to stray. And that's
real זנות, znut, that's adultery. And that would be in that category.
רבי עקיבא אומר זה המשהה בתו בוגרת. Rabbi Akiva omer zeh hamasheh
bito bogeret. It's a man who waits with his daughter who once
she's of age and she's now בוגרת, bogeret, right? So she's now
sort of sexually mature. She's all of twelve and a half. But
again normally you would—the assumption is that she'd be married off before
that age as a קטנה ktana or as a נערה. na'arah. And
now he wants her to remain around the house. Why does he
want her to remain at the house? We'll see in a minute.
Maybe he wants her to continue to work for him, maybe he
doesn't have a wife or whatever, he needs her to help raise
the kids or to cook the food. Or maybe he's trying to
get a higher dowry. That's the way the מהרש"א Maharsha reads it,
we'll see why in a minute. For whatever reason, he's leaving her
around. But she's now sexually mature. And now she is going to
be, maybe tempted sexually, and actually have sex outside of marriage. So
this by the way I should say, certainly suggests that it's not
only limited to the case of like prostitution. Again, maybe it doesn't
mean a context of a committed relationship, it's somewhere between those two,
casually she'll be tempted. But anyway that is זנות znut outside of
the context of marriage. And if you're setting that up a situation
that can have that, you're just asking for trouble. That's the prohibition
of אל תחלל את בתך להזנותה. al techalel et bitcha lehaznotah. אמר
רב כהנא משום רבי עקיבא. amar Rav Kahana mishum Rabbi Akiva. אין
לך עני בישראל אלא רשע ערום, ein lecha ani beyisrael ela rasha
arum, you have no poor person in Israel except for the sly
evil person. How these combine we'll see in a minute. והמשיא בתו
בוגרת, vehamasi bitcho bogeret, and the man that waits to marry off
his daughter until she is, and even while she's now בוגרת, bogeret,
she's sexually mature, he still hasn't married her off. המשהה, hamishaheh, excuse
me, not המשיא. hamasi. So the Gemara says אטו המשהה בתו בוגרת
לאו רשע ערום? atu hamishaheh bitcho bogeret lav rasha arum? That isn't
a רשע ערום? rasha arum? What does it mean by רשע ערום?
rasha arum? It means that he is like, he's a רשע rasha
because he's basically causing his daughter to be tempted sexually, but it's
ערום arum because he's sly about it, he's doing it for some
ulterior motive or maybe he's even claiming, the way the מהרש"א Maharsha
says as I said before, he's claiming no, I'm doing it for
a good reason, I'm doing it because I want her to get
a big dowry even though he's really doing it just so she
can support him. Okay, so that's the case of רשע ערום. rasha
arum. So what do you mean by calling these different cases? So
אמר אביי, amar Abaye, אביי Abaye says really it was all one
thing. אמר אביי הכי קאמר, amar Abaye hachi ka'amar, this is what
it means. איזהו עני רשע ערום, eizehu ani rasha arum, who is
a poor person who is being a רשע rasha and being ערום
arum about it? זה המשהה בתו בוגרת. zeh hamishaheh bitcho bogeret. He's
leaving over his daughter, he's not marrying off his daughter even though
she's a בוגרת. bogeret. So because he's an עני ani he needs
extra help in the house, can't hire a servant or something, and
he's a רשע rasha because he's tempting her sexually, exposing her to
temptation, and he's ערום arum because he claims, like the way the
מהרש"א Maharsha says, that he's doing it all for a good reason.
ואמר רב כהנא משום רבי עקיבא, ve'amar Rav Kahana mishum Rabi Akiva,
הוי זהיר מן היועצך לפי דרכו. hevei zahir min hayo'atzcha lefi darko.
Be, so this same רבי Rabi Rav Kahana, it's the same רב
כהנא Rav Kahana in the name of רבי עקיבא, Rabi Akiva, it
seems a little unrelated, but be careful about a person who gives
you advice but really it's self-serving advice. So the מהרש"א Maharsha says
that that's this case. He's telling the daughter, hey, wait, wait around,
you'll get a big dowry, let's hold off, but he's really doing
it for self-serving because he wants her around the house to take
care of the domestic needs. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב, amar Rav
Yehuda amar Rav, so now we're going to end with some related
אגדתות. aggadot. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב המשיא בתו לזקן, amar Rav
Yehuda amar Rav hamasi bitcho lezaken, if somebody marries off his daughter
to an old man, והמשיא אשה לבנו קטן, vehamasi isha livno katan,
or the flip, marries off his underage son to a woman who's
already of age, והמחזיר אבידה לכותי, vehamachzir aveidah lekhuti, I have it
says לכותי, lekhuti, it said לגוי, legoy, and somebody returns an אבידה
aveidah to a non-Jew, to a Gentile, עליו הכתוב אומר למען ספות
הרווה את הצמאה, alav hakatuv omer lema'an sfot haravah et hatzme'ah, in
order, somebody's going to do this thing to add the sated to
the thirsty. לא יאבה השם סלוח לו, lo yoveh Hashem slo'ach lo,
God won't forgive him. So what does this mean, adding the sated
to the thirsty? So רש"י Rashi says very appropriately, these are matches,
we're worried about the אבידה aveidah in a minute, these are matches
that one of them has sexual desire, thirsty, and the other is
sated, doesn't have sexual desire. Either the old guy is sated because
he's old in general and also he's had it in his life
throughout his long life, but he's also no longer interested, or the
young person who's not yet of age. So they're the sated people
and you're matching them together with the woman who is thirsty, who
has
sexual desire, that is asking for trouble. The מהרש"א Maharsha says a
slight variation because למען ספות הרווה את הצמאה lema'an sfot haravah et
hatzme'ah means that somebody who beforehand, the רמב"ן Ramban says this, it
means that you beforehand you weren't tempted, you had no interest in
something, you were sated as it were, but there you sort of
forced yourself to be or whatever you put yourself in a situation
which creates a desire where there wasn't any. And this particularly in
the case of like sexual desire. So the מהרש"א Maharsha says, so
he says that this woman, maybe she was sated before she was
being married off, she's only anyway, if she, maybe she's a קטנה,
ktana, maybe she's whatever, she's not necessarily sexually tempted. But then the
father goes and he marries her to this old guy and she
actually is in some type of a context which now she's exposed
to sex and so on, but then it's not satisfying her and
then she's going to go and stray. So it turns a case
that was sated, the woman was sated not just the man and
it made her and it tempted her now made her sort of
have a sexual appetite, it awakened a sexual appetite. Okay, so that's
that. By the way also תוספות Tosafot points out an interesting question
about why is the case about the minor son, since when is
there a rabbinic marriage for a minor son? And he's not really
certain about that, and okay so maybe it's that the guy married
off his son under age and it's not even really halachically recognized
yet, not even rabbinically. And then it's very interesting, well would that
be considered a type of a זנות zenut to be doing something
in that type of a context which in practical terms they're considered
married but halachically not? So תוספות Tosafot has that interesting question. As
far as the issue about returning the lost object, I would sort
of say in terms of the idea of sated and hungry. thirsty.
I would have said that, you know, רש"י Rashi says what it
means is, and I don't get the sated and thirsty metaphor here,
that you're- it's- you know, since you're returning a lost object to
a non-Jew as well as to a Jew, it shows you're just
doing it because you think it's the right thing, not because it's
a מצוה. mitzvah. So that's problematic. And those I guess the sated
and thirsty is one case there's a מצוה mitzvah one case there's
not a מצוה, mitzvah, which is very strange because you would think
that you would want to apply the implicit ethics and morality in
the מצוות mitzvos and certainly just look at בין אדם לחבירו ben
adam l'chavero מצוות mitzvas also, you know, to do it not just
from the ציווי tzivoi perspective. Famous רמב"ם Rambam in שמונה פרקים, Shmona
Perakim, you know, one could say that's why we don't make ברכות
brachas before בין אדם לחבירו ben adam l'chavero מצוות, mitzvos, it's not
just- it doesn't get its significance just from the ציווי tzivoi perspective.
I would have said that it's more a perception that non-Jews have
money and Jews don't have money, I guess the reverse of contemporary
stereotypes, but in the place where the Rab- where חז"ל Chazal were
living, you know, the non-Jew were in control and they had and
they had, you know, the control economy and so on. So why
are you giving this thing to somebody who's already sated if you
don't have a הלכתי halachic obligation? Should we keep it for ourselves,
we're thirsty or something like that. You know, anyway, obviously that raises
important questions about the whole morality of not returning lost objects to
non-Jews and so on. Okay, we're going to bracket that for now.
Let's keep on going. מתיב, Meisiv, asks on this, this- I- idea
that you're not supposed to marry off your daughter- excuse me, or-
you're not supposed to marry off your son when he's still a
minor. So we say like this: האוהב את אשתו כגופו, Ha'ohev es
ishto k'gufo, if a man loves his wife as himself, והמכבדה יותר
מגופו, v'hamichabdo yoser migufo, and shows her more כבוד, kavod, honor, than
he shows himself- and here רש"י Rashi just says buy nice clothes,
I mean honor when we think about כיבוד אב ואם, kibud av
va'em, right, is to sort of take care of their needs, feeding,
clothing, you know, doing everything that's attending to them. Okay, so that
as opposed to אהבה, ahava, one also
wonders by אהבה ahava do they mean the emotional אהבה ahava do
they mean more the way it expresses itself like ואהבת לרעך כמוך,
v'ahavta l'reiacha kamocha, do to them like you would do to yourself?
If anyway, interesting phrase right there. האוהב את אשתו כגופו והמכבדה יותר
מגופו. Ha'ohev es ishto k'gufo v'hamichabdo yoser migufo. והמדריך בניו ובנותיו בדרך
ישרה, V'hamadrich banav u'vnosav b'derech yeshara, you like- you give הדרכה, hadracha,
you put your kids on the straight and narrow, you know, you-
you bring them up and educate them in terms of proper behavior.
והמשיאן סמוך לפרקן, V'hamisiyan samuch l'firkan, and you marry them off near
to their age of maturity, so here's the idea, right? You- you
marry them off before they'll be tempted sexually- sexually. By the way,
you know, these are- really raises, you know, when we realize according
to- that nowadays a major challenge people have is all the prohibitions
around sex outside of marriage, especially if the woman is a נידה
niddah and so on, and like with the איסור נגיעה, issur negiah,
even sexual touch. Anyway, for the Rabbis they solved it by marrying
off the kids, right, before they got בר bar and בת מצוה,
bas mitzvahed, so- therefore before they were sexually tempted they were already
married off. עליו הכתוב אומר, Alav hakasuv omer, regarding that type of
a person the verse says, וידעת כי שלום אהלך, v'yadata ki shalom
ohalecha, you'll know your tent, meaning your wife and your kids are
all in peace, everybody is taken care of, ופקדת נוך, ufakadta navecha,
you will visit your tent, ולא תחטא, v'lo secheta, you will not
sin, and they also presumably won't sin, you know, your kids, etc.
Anyway, so it says you're marrying off your son right before he's
בר מצוה. bar mitzvahed. But we just said you're not supposed to
marry off your son if he's under age. So the גמרא Gemara
says: סמוך לפרקן שאני. Samuch l'firkan shani. No, no, no. Near their
age of maturity, like, you know, a few months before they get
בר bar and בת מצוה, bas mitzvahed, that's okay. The problem is
that doing it when they're still significantly young. All right, fine. So
that's the idea. Don't marry off your daughter to an elderly man,
don't marry off your son, maybe even your daughter- again, this is
נישואין nisuin not קידושין, kiddushin, קידושין kiddushin was- done younger- you know,
before they are sexually mature, but once they're sexually mature get them
married off as quickly as possible so they're not tempted. Or when
they're about to be sexually mature. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. האוהב את
שכיניו והמקרב את קרוביו, Ha'ohev es shchenav v'hamakarev es krovav, somebody who
loves his neighbor- meaning builds up a sense of community- and brings
his- I love the phrase מקרב את קרוביו, makarev es krovav, they're
already your relatives but you bring them close. As we all know,
people are not always close with their relatives. והנושא את בת אחותו,
V'hanosei es bas achoso, and somebody who marries- that's probably why it's
brought in- this issue about getting married, and also we spoke about
all the prohibitions of marrying daughter and step-daughter, and here you're דווקא
davka supposed to marry your niece. והנושא את בת אחותו, V'hanosei es
bas achoso, your sister's daughter. והמלווה סלע לעני בשעת דוחקו, V'hamilveh sela
l'ani b'shas dochako, and somebody who lends a סלע sela to a
poor person when he really needs it, you know, and he's in
pressure and you- act- come in and you save him, you know,
because he didn't know where he was going to get the money
he needed. I think they actually did actually a survey about or
whatever, like how- what would people do if they needed 300 dollars
for an emergency, like would they have someone to go to? You
know, some medical emergency or something. And like the percentage of people-
of Americans who said that they would not be able to get
300 dollars if they needed for an emergency was like mind-boggling. I
forget what it was, but it was
very... Anyway, just as how much we don't often appreciate how so
many people are like living, you know, hand to mouth. So anyway,
so here if you do any of those things, אז תקרא וה'
יענה Az tikra vaHashem ya'aneh regarding him the verse says אז תקרא
וה' יענה Az tikra vaHashem ya'aneh like we read just the other
day on יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. What does this have to do
with אז תקרא וה' יענה? Az tikra vaHashem ya'aneh? So רש"י Rashi
says, because right before that it said מבשרך לא תתעלם, Mibesarcha lo
titalem, do not do not hide yourself from your flesh, and that's
of course so here it's like marrying, you know, your your sister's
daughter, you know, that close closeness of family, bringing your relatives close,
even your neighbors, creating, you know, that sense of those that are
close to you, right, not the standards of universally or, you know,
everybody deserves equal sort of love and treatment, you can't love everybody
equally and the power of showing that to those that are close
to you. And it also says, right, that when an עני, Ani,
you know, it speaks about פרוס לרעב לחמך, Paros lara'ev lachmecha, give
bread to, you know, the hungry one. So the end of it
is אז תקרא וה' יענה. Az tikra vaHashem ya'aneh. Okay, תנו רבנן,
Tanu Rabbanan, now one last thing about the issue here about the
mother and, you know, about the mother-in-law and grandmother-in-law and so on.
It says באש ישרפו אתו ואתהן, Ba'esh yisrefu oto ve'ethen, him and
them, you know, that's פשט, Pshat, them. But who are the them?
It's about a man with his wife and his wife's mother. Now
the פשט Pshat of the פסוקים Psukim is that you also the
wife, but the חז"ל Chazal do not understand it that you burn
also the wife, but חז"ל Chazal don't understand it that way because
the wife was the היתר, Heter, right? There's no איסור Issur for
a man to be to be sleeping with his wife, even if
he goes and sleeps with his wife's mother, the prohibition, the transgression
was the wife's mother, the wife didn't do anything wrong, why would
you kill the wife? So the גמרא Gemara so
that creates this, so you know maybe the פסוקים Psukim maybe in
the פשט Pshat I don't know, means they're all doing it all
at once or something. But anyway, but for חז"ל Chazal certainly the
wife is out of the picture. So what's the אתהן, Ethen, the
plural? So אתו ואת אחת מהן, Oto ve'et achat mehen,
him and one of them, דברי רבי ישמעאל, Divrei Rabbi Yishmael, which
seems not פשט Pshat in the פסוקים, Psukim, we'll see what the
גמרא Gemara does with him in a minute. רבי עקיבא אומר אתו
ואת שתיהן, Rabbi Akiva omer oto ve'et shteihen,
both of them. Now what both of them? Obviously it doesn't mean
the wife. So let's take a look. מאי בינייהו? Mai beinaihu? אמר
אביי משמעות דורשין איכא
בינייהו. Amar Abaye mashma'ut dorshin ika beinaihu. They're not disagreeing halachically, they're
just arguing what to do with the פסוק. Pasuk. רבי ישמעאל סבר
אתו ואתהן, Rabbi Yishmael savar oto ve'ethen, אתו ואת אחת מהן. Oto
ve'et achat mehen. How does he get אתהן Ethen and them to
mean one of them? שכן בלשון יווני קורין לאחת הינא. Sheken bilshon
Yavani korin le'achat Hina. In Greek they call one הינא Hina which
I assume is like one one הין, Hin, same thing, חז"ל Chazal
often the ה Hey is, you know, it's
spelled with a ה Hey and it's really without the whatever. So
it seems like that that's one, okay, so that's how we read
it, אתהן Ethen one of them. Okay. ואימא חמותו מדרישא אתיא Ve'eima
chamoto midreisha atya he would learn
grandmother-in-law from the דרשה Drasha like we did earlier, learning it from
the same way we went down, we went up and so on.
רבי עקיבא סבר Rabbi Akiva savar no, אתו ואתהן, Oto ve'ethen, both
of them. Both of who? Not the wife and the and the
and the mother-in-law, but the mother-in-law and the
grandmother-in-law. אתו ואת
שתיהן. Oto ve'et shteihen. ואימא חמותו הכא כתיבא, Ve'eima chamoto hacha ktiva,
and that's if you remember we said that before, according to רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva grandmother-in-law is in the פסוק. Pasuk. So it says
if a man takes a woman and her daughter, it's talking about
the grandmother-in-law and her daughter and the mother-in-law. So that's two prohibitions
of wife's mother and wife's grandmother, okay, and but they're both being
killed not because they were together and the problem was them being
together, but because they're both mother or grandmother of the wife. Okay,
and that's what he learns the אתהן Ethen the plural. Of course,
not obviously everybody's clear the wife is out of it, and from
him grandmother-in-law is in the פסוק. Pasuk. Okay. ואימא חמותו הכא כתיבא.
Ve'eima chamoto hacha ktiva. רבא אמר חמותו לאחר מיתה איכא בינייהו. Rava
amar chamoto le'achar mita ika beinaihu. No, no,
no, there's a real significant halachic debate between them. What would be
the story of mother-in-law after the wife is no longer around? So
after the wife is dead. רבי ישמעאל סבר חמותו לאחר מיתה בשריפה,
Rabbi Yishmael savar chamoto le'achar mita bisreifah, she's burnt. It's the same
punishment, but אתהן את אחת מהן Ethen et achat mehen means
even if only one of them is around, the wife isn't around
anymore, it's still prohibited with the wife's mother,
which does not sound like it from the פסוקים Psukim but okay.
רבי עקיבא סבר איסורא בעלמא. Rabbi Akiva savar issura be'alma. No, it
means אתהן את שתיהן, Ethen et shteihen, not that you burn the
wife, but only when the wife is still around. Okay, but if
the wife is not around, I assume the same would be true
if you divorced her, then it would be prohibited, how prohibited, rabbinically,
רש"י Rashi says it's one of the ארורים Arurim and so on,
but it would not be a biblical violation of one of the
עריות, Arayot, it would not be punishable by death and so on.
That's a pretty big debate. Okay, that is the end of שריפה,
Sreifah, the case basically of variations of mother
whatever, mother-in-law grandmother-in-law.